The Stoeckel Family Papers
Yale University Music Library
The Stoeckel Family Papers
1906-1971
Misc. Ms. 247
Yale University Music Library
0.25
(1 box)
Papers of Carl Stoeckel (1858-1925) and Ellen Battell Stoeckel (1851-1939), the founders of the Norfolk Music Festival, with special emphasis on Jean Sibelius and Samuel Coleridge-Taylor, from whom the Stoeckels commissioned new works for the festival
Stoeckel Family
Downes, Olin, 1886-1955
Conditions Governing Access
The Papers are open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Stoeckel Family Papers were established in the Music Library of Yale University by Ellen Battell Stoeckel in 1926.
Arrangement
In 3 series as follows: I. Writings about Sibelius and Coleridge-Taylor. II. Correspondence. III. Miscellany.
Scope and Contents
The Stoeckel Family Papers consist primarily of Carl Stoeckel's typed reminiscences of visits made by Jean Sibelius and Samuel Coleridge-Taylor to the Stoeckel Family Estate in Norfolk, CT. Additional writings about Sibelius, by Olin Downes and Karl Ekman, are also included. The Papers also hold a small number of letters between members of the Stoeckel Family and Horatio Parker, David Stanley Smith, and Eva J. O'Meara, as well as a biographical sketch of Robbins Battell Stoeckel and a copy of Ellen Battell Stoeckel's will.
Biographical / Historical
The Stoeckel and Battell families both played crucial roles in the development of music at Yale University. Gustave Jacob Stoeckel (1819-1907) was the first professor of music at Yale. Robbins Battell (1819-1895) was a generous Yale philanthropist as well as an amateur composer. Stoeckel's papers and some of Battell's compositions are preserved in the Yale Music Library as MSS 27 and Misc. Ms. 157, respectively. In 1895, Stoeckel's son Carl (1858-1925) married Battell's daughter Ellen (1851-1939). Carl had previously been Robbins Battell's secretary. In 1899, Ellen and Carl Stoeckel established the Litchfield County Choral Union, and this group's concerts proved to be the beginning of an important summer music festival in Norfolk, Connecticut, where the Stoeckels lived. In 1906 they built the Norfolk Music Shed to house the Festival's concerts. Renowned performers such as Sergei Rachmaninoff, Fritz Kreisler, and Lillian Nordica appeared at the Festival, and the Stoeckels commissioned new works from many composers, including Jean Sibelius, Samuel Coleridge-Taylor, Horatio Parker, Henry Gilbert, and Victor Herbert; the Stoeckel Family Papers are largely devoted to Carl's recollections of Sibelius and Coleridge-Taylor. The festival went into abeyance after Carl's death in 1925, but when Ellen died in 1939, her will established the Ellen Battell Stoeckel Trust to revive the festival, in collaboration with Yale. The Norfolk Music Festival still takes place every summer at the family estate.
Music -- Connecticut -- Norfolk; Coleridge-Taylor, Samuel, 1875-1912; O'Meara, Eva Judd; Parker, Horatio W. (Horatio William), 1863-1919; Sibelius, Jean, 1865-1957; Smith, David Stanley, 1877-1949; Stoeckel, Carl, 1858-1925; Stoeckel, Ellen Battell; Stoeckel, Robbins Battell, 1872-1951
- Writings about Sibelius and Coleridge-Taylor, Series I
  - Jean Sibelius / Olin Downes., Downes, Olin, 1886-1955; [33] leaves, bound; 27 cm. (Box 1)
    General
    Typescript, probably by Carl Stoeckel.
    Sibelius's appearance as conductor of his own works at a concert at Norfolk on June 4, 1914, is mentioned.
    Photocopy master.
  - Sibelius at Norfolk: quoted from "Jean Sibelius" / by Karl Ekman., Ekman, Karl; 11 leaves, bound; 29 cm. (Box 1)
    Originally published in Ekman's Jean Sibelius, Helsingfors, 1935.
  - Coleridge-Taylor / [Carl Stoeckel], Stoeckel, Carl, 1858-1925; 22 leaves, bound; 27 cm. (Box 1)
    Typescript.
    A description of Samuel Coleridge-Taylor's visits to Norfolk in 1906 and 1909, during which his works were performed.
  - Some recollections of the visit of Sibelius to America in 1914 / [Carl Stoeckel]., Stoeckel, Carl, 1858-1925; 34, A-M leaves, bound; 27 cm. (Box 1)
    Downes on Sibelius: ovation to Sibelius. Krehbiel on Sibelius: an interesting point.
    Typescript, probably by Carl Stoeckel, signed by him on p. 34.
    Last two items quoted from unknown sources.
  - "Some recollections of the visit of Sibelius to America in 1914." Scandinavian Studies 43 (1971): 53-88., Stoeckel, Carl, 1858-1925 (Box 1)
    [entire volume saved]
- Correspondence, Series II
  - Mostly library correspondence to and from Mr. Mrs. Carl Stoeckel and Robbins Battell Stoeckel, 1916-1945; 114 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes 3 typescript lists of music given to the library by Mrs. Carl Stoeckel.
- Miscellany, Series III
  - Robbins Battell Stoeckel. Lawyer, Norfolk, Connecticut: from the Twenty-five year record, class of ninety-three Yale College., 2 sheets; 28 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Originally published in the Twenty-five year record, class of ninety-three Yale College, c1918.
  - Last will and testament of Ellen Battell Stoeckel: dated, August 8, 1935: date of death, May 5, 1939., 10 p., bound; 27 cm. (Box 1, Folder 2)